WAMU 045
DCPL Special Collections - MLK Library
WAMU Broadcast Collection
1998–2004
DCPL Special Collections - MLK Library
WAMU-FM (Radio station: Washington, D.C.)
045
14 Boxes
Biographical / Historical
WAMU began as a carrier current student radio station on the campus of The American University on July 28, 1951. The station received a commercial FM license and made its first FM broadcast on October 23, 1961. Since then, WAMU has continued to provide public affairs and educational programing joined the National Educational Radio Network. In 1971 the station became a founding member of National Public Radio (NPR). Initially, in 1967 WAMU began programing bluegrass music, which included shows such as the Lee Michael Demsey Show and the Ray Davis Show. The station also hosted an annual bluegrass concert and a yearly Pickin' in the Glen, which featured many top performers. The station changed its programing in 2002, transitioning its main channel to an all-news and public affairs format. The bluegrass component became a separate online and HD2 station. WAMU is home to a team of award-winning local reports and acclaimed talk radio hosts including Diane Rehm and Kojo Nnamdi. When WETA, a fellow public radio station, changed its format to all classical music in 2007, WAMU became Washington DC's only full-time NPR station.
Custodial History
WAMU, in 1998, began depositing in the Archives audiotapes of broadcasts related to local D.C. current affairs and history under an agreement with the Library. WAMU holds copyright to the tape library and all content. Library patrons may listen to the tapes only within Special Collections.
Scope and Contents
The collection contains 679 audio cassettes containing recordings primarily of three weekly shows, Metro Connection, Public Interest (DC Politics Hour) and the Kojo Nnamdi Show dating between 1998 and 2004. All show content is related to local D.C. current affairs and history.
The collection also contains editorials on D.C. political issues, most often prepared by Mark Plotkin, as well as some 1-hour segments from Public Interest, which relate to local Washington, D.C. matters. Significant featured series in the collection include: recordings of 1998 mayoral debates and candidate forums sponsored by WAMU; the 20th Century Washington series which aired on Metro Connection in 1999 to mark the close of the 20th century by reporting on significant periods or events in the city's history
Politics and government; Neighborhoods; Radio programs; Audio
- Series 1: Local Interest, 1998-2002
  Scope and Contents
  The series contains 287 audio recordings of Local Interest and includes but is not limited to the following programs: Public Interest; DC Politics Hour; DC Politics Hour with Mark Plotkin; and the Diane Rehm Show.
  - 51 audio tapes, June 24 1998-February 5 1999 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - 50 audio tapes, February 12 1999-September 3 1999 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - 51 audio tapes, September 9 1999-March 20 2000 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - 51 audio tapes, March 22 2000-March 2 2001 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - 50 audio tapes, March 2 2001-January 18 2002 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - 34 audio tapes, January 25 2002-September 27 2002 (Box 6, Folder 1)
- Series 2: Metro Connection, 1998-2004
  The series contains 289 audio recording of the Metro Connection Program.
  - 17 audio tapes, February 27 1998-October 10 1998 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - 51 audio tapes, October 24 1998-November 20 1999 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - 50 audio tapes, November 23 1999-April 28 2001 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - 51 audio tapes, May 5 2001-May 18 2002 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - 52 audio tapes, June 1 2002-June 27 2003 (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - 52 audio tapes, July 11, 2003-August 20, 2004 (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - audiotapes, August 27, 2004-December 17, 2004 (Box 12, Folder 1)
- Series 3: Kojo Nnamdi, 2002-2004
  The series contains 103 audio recordings of the Kojo Nnamdi Show.
  - Audio tapes, October 4, 2002-October 31, 2003 (Box 13, Folder 1)
  - Audio tapes, November 7, 2003- December 17, 2004 (Box 14, Folder 1)